Preliminary Inventory to the Paul Buhle Papers TAM 171
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Paul Buhle Papers
Bulk, 1960-1995
1913-1995, (Bulk 1960-1995)
TAM 171
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
7.25 linear feet (16 boxes)
Paul Buhle, Senior Lecturer in the Department of History and American Civilization, Brown University (2002- ), is a scholar of U.S. radicalism, in particular its cultural manifestations, and of the immigrant left. The author or editor of some two dozen books, he was an active participant in the New Left of the 1960s-70s, notably as editor of Radical America. The papers contain correspondence, published and unpublished writings, research files relating to the immigrant left in the U.S. and to C. L. R. James, and a collection of post-1960 radical humor and political satire, much of it in the form of graphic art, including caricatures and cartoons, and comics. NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Buhle, Paul, 1944-
Box 1-16
Provenance
Donated by Paul Buhle, 1990s.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Historical/Biographical Note
Paul Buhle, Senior Lecturer in the Department of History and American Civilization, Brown University (2002-), is a scholar of U.S. radicalism, in particular its cultural manifestations, and of the immigrant left. He was an active participant in the New Left of the 1960s-70s, notably as editor of Radical America. He is the author or editor of some two dozen books, including Students for a Democratic Society: A Graphic History(2008); Wobblies! A Graphic History of the Industrial Workers of the World(2005); Radical Hollywood:The Untold Story behind America's Favorite Movies(2002); Images of American Radicalism(1998); The Immigrant Left in the United States(1996); Encyclopedia of the American Left(1990), Marxism in the United States: Remapping the History of the American Left(1987); C. L. R. James, His Life and Work(1986), and Labor's Joke Book(1985). He was also one of the organizers of and chief contributors to the Oral History of the American Left(1984- ), a project of the Tamiment Library, NYU.
Scope and Content Note
The papers contain correspondence, published and unpublished writings, research files relating to the immigrant left in the U.S. and to C. L. R. James, and a collection of post-1960 radical humor and political satire, much of it in the form of graphic art, including caricatures and cartoons, and comics. The collection is described at the box level. NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Arrangement
The box descriptions are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into one series:
I, Paul Buhle Papers.
Separated Material
A large file of posters, flyers, and original artwork, including artwork for Morning Freiheit cartoons by William Gropper, was separated to the Non-Print department.
Buhle, Paul, 1944-; James, C. L. R., (Cyril Lionel Robert), 1901-1989.; Caricatures and cartoons |z United States.; Caricatures and cartoons.; Comic books.; Communism |z United States.; Correspondence.; Czech Americans.; Hungarian Americans.; Manuscripts (document genre); New Left |z United States.; Political cartoons |z United States.; Political cartoons.; Political satire, American.; Radicalism |z United States.; Radicals |z United States; Slavic Americans.; Socialism |z United States.; Wit and humor, American.
- Series I: Paul Buhle Papers.
  - Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1981 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1986 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1994 (Box 4)
  - Graphics, Photos, ca.1960s-1980s (Box 5)
  - Immigrant Left (Czechs-Hungarians), ca.1960s-1980s (Box 6)
  - Immigrant Left (Hungarians-Slavs), ca.1960s-1980s (Box 7)
  - James, C. L. R., ca.1960s-1980s (Box 8)
  - Radical Humor Movement (I), ca.1960s-1980s (Box 9)
  - Radical Humor Movement (II), ca.1960s-1980s (Box 10)
  - Radical Humor Movement (III), ca.1960s-1980s (Box 11)
  - Writings, Unpublished (undergraduate and graduate), 1960s-1970s (Box 12)
  - Writings, Unpublished, 1970s (Box 13)
  - Writings, Unpublished, 1970s, 1980s (Box 14)
  - Writings, Published Writings (newspapers, articles, reviews, etc.), 1967-1995 (Box 15)
  - Yiddish ads, cartoons, and caricatures, Undated, 1913, 1940s-1980s (Box 16)